[MUSIC]
評估樣本數
When you design a new study, one of the most important things to keep in
設計一項新研究的重要課題之一是
mind is the sample size that you want to collect.
決定要收集的樣本數目
We see that in many studies sample sizes are too small.
許多研究文獻的樣本數都很小
And I want to give you some practical advice on how to decide upon a sample size
這一講要給你一些決定樣本數的可實行建議
for a future study that you'll do.
So if you would design a new study, how would you determine the sample size?
設計一項新研究時，你如何決定樣本數
Take a moment to think about this.
這值得花點時間考慮
There are different approaches to do this, and we'll talk about them in this lecture.
決定方法有很多，以下談談這些方法
What I used to do, when I was doing my PhD, was either use exactly the same
我進行自已的博士論文研究時，曾考慮過
number of participants as a previous study had used or I would use a heuristic.
要收集與之前研究相同的人數
還是採用一些訣竅
In my time, it was quite common to use a sample size of 15 participants for
那時候獨立組設計習慣每一組招募15人
each between-subjects condition.
Nowadays, this number has increased a little bit.
製作這個課程時，數目已經稍微增加
I see that people very often use about 25 participants for
我看到多數獨立組研究是每一組招募25人
each between-subjects condition.
But is this sufficient?
但是這樣子就夠了嗎？
And if not, what should you do instead of relying on these heuristics?
如果不夠，新的研究該怎麼做？
Now first, let's realize what the problem is if you collect small samples.
首先讓我們搞清楚收集樣本太小會有什麼問題
Small samples always have large variation leading to very inaccurate estimates.
小樣本總是造成較大變異
連帶導致不良的估計
But when you perform an hypothesis test, they also lead to high Type 2 error rates.
小樣本還會造成偏高的型二錯誤率
Which means that you perform a study, you do a statistical test, and
也就是小樣本資料的統計檢定
even when there is true effect, the test result is not statistically significant.
在真實效果存在時，檢定不顯著的錯誤
It's important to prevent this, both Type 2 errors and inaccurate estimates.
型二錯誤和不良的估計都是要避免的
This is a nice visualization by Schonbrodt and Perugini who show
Schonbrodt與Perugini做了不錯的視覺化範例
how the variation in data decreases as the sample size becomes larger.
展示資料的變異下降與增加樣本數的關係
From the left to the right, we see
a continuously increasing sample size.
橫軸由左至右的連續數值代表增加的樣本數
We also see a black line.
留意每一條黑線的走勢
And in this case, the black line is actually the effect size estimate from
每條線是從收集的資料，以對應的樣本數
a study they performed as they collected more and more data.
計算得到的真實效果量
So the effect size was calculated after every participants and
也就是收完一位參與者資料
it's plotted here as a black line.
就計算一次效果量的總成
You can see that there's a huge drop in the effect size.
好幾條線的走勢很明顯是下降的
And what they show is that actually such variation is possible,
整體也顯示真實資料的變異程度
because small samples have very large variation.
樣本越少變異越大
I referred to this as sailing the seas of chaos into what Schonbrodt and
我把這樣的景觀比喻為穿越暴風雨
Perugini named the corridor of stability.
抵達寧靜迴廊之旅
On the left you see huge waves.
圖左邊的好似濤天巨浪
If you have small samples, then your data is riding these huge waves.
小樣本的估計值猶如被浪頭頂著的小船
Effects can be very large or very small.
效果量可大可小
The variation is substantial.
全由資料變異決定
Now as you enter the corridor of stability, as Schonbrodt &
進入Schonbrodt與Perugini所稱的寧靜迴廊時
Perugini call this, you see that the variation becomes much less severe.
資料變異變得沒那麼劇烈
There's still some variation around the true effect size estimate, but
雖然真實效果量的估計值還是有些變異
at this point, you're making very accurate estimations.
過這這一點之後，估計值明顯更正確
Now we see that researchers failed to take the sample size into account when they
採用小樣本資料的研究，研究者很難提出
design new studies.
有說服力的解釋
And this is nothing new.
這並不是新聞
We've known this for about 50 years, and only now it is very slowly changing.
50年前就有人提出警告，但學術界改變很慢
In certain literatures where sample sizes are very expensive, so
在某些域收集資料成本極高
if you want to collect a large number of people, you have to have a lot of money,
經費充裕才有可能收集大樣本資料的研究
such as neuroscience, where we put people in fMRI scanners,
像是fMRI這類收集人腦活動的研究
we see that there's really a huge power failure.
這篇論文指出嚴重的檢定力失效問題
Studies are severely underpowered.
也就是多數神經科學研究的檢定力過低
Interestingly, people have been saying this for
有趣的是這問題吵了這麼多年
years and years, and there are even papers that say that the studies of
還有新論文指出設定統計檢定力的研究
statistical power don't have any effect on the power of studies.
對於提昇研究檢定力幫助有限
This is slightly depressing, because here I'm talking about how you should
正在告訴你如何設計良好的研究，看到一篇
design well-powered studies, even though past research has shown that this
論文說這些努力都是徒勞的
does not have an effect on what researchers really do.
不免讓人有些喪氣
But on the other hand, we see the things are now really changing.
另一方面，情勢也正在改變
More and more journals are requiring what's known as a sample size
越來越多期刊要求作者提供樣本數決定策略
justification.
You need to explicitly write down why you selected this specific sample size.
作者要明確說明決定樣本數的理由
So I seriously think that in the future we'll see a big change in this
我預見一些特定領域將有很大的變化
specific area.
We see that studies in psychology often have very low statistical power.
現在已知許多心理學研究的檢定力偏低
Estimates average around 50%,
估計50%左右
which means that, even if you have a true hypothesis, you only have
也就是說，就算有一個明確的假設
a 50% probability of actually observing a statistically significant finding.
只有50%的機會能獲得統計顯著的結果
I think that if people realized this,
如果一般人都能了解這點
they would seriously reconsider doing the study,
會重新考慮當這行研究人員的意義
because they only have 50% probability of finding an effect when it's there.
因為已知的發現只有50%是真的
That doesn't seem to be worth all the effort to collect this data.
那何必要拼死拼活地收集資料
Now, one reason for low powered studies is that people don't really
造成低檢定力研究橫行的原因之一是
think about how to design their study and especially the sample size of their study.
多數研究者並未仔細設計研究，特別是樣本數
But people use heuristics instead.
多數人都依賴慣例或秘訣
Now, heuristics are always wrong.
多數慣例是錯誤的
You should never rely on heuristics to plan the sample size,
現在的你不該依此決定樣本數
no matter what the recommendation of this heuristic is.
不論你多認同相關的建議
Whether it’s 10, 20, 50 people, you should always use a better approach and
不管要收集10,20還是50位參與者
應該要使用更好的方法
more informed justification of your sample size.
還有有所本的樣本數評估策略
Nowadays, journals ask you do this.
已經有期刊如此要求作者
So you need to justify the sample size of a study.
有評估樣本數時
The justification depends on the goal that you want to achieve.
應根據你的研究目標做評估
Let's consider different goals.
讓我們看看怎麼做
In this graph, we can see again correlation between two variables.
這是兩個變項的散佈圖及相關係數
We see a rather wide confidence interval.
其中的信賴區間範圍很寬
In this case there are only ten observations.
這個例子只有十筆資料
So the confidence interval is really wide.
才讓信賴區間這麼寬
If we increase the sample size to 100 participants,
若增加到100筆資料
we see that the confidence interval becomes much more narrow.
信賴區間明顯變窄
If your goal is to design a study that will accurately
如果目的是想要獲得正確效果量的估計值
estimate the true effect size, then having a sample size
達到可接受的估計正確性是決定樣本數的重點
that allows you to achieve a certain accuracy is a good goal.
So one approach is to plan for accuracy.
所以估計值的正確性是一種好方法
Select a sample size based on the width of a confidence interval.
也就是根據信賴區間的寬度決定樣本數
A classic paper on this is Maxwell, Kelley and Rausch.
如果你想以估計正確性評估樣本數
建議參考Maxwell, Kelley與Rausch的經典論文
I recommend that you can read this if you want to know how to design studies
如果你想以估計正確性評估樣本數
建議參考Maxwell, Kelley與Rausch的經典論文
based on accuracy.
如果你想以估計正確性評估樣本數
建議參考Maxwell, Kelley與Rausch的經典論文
The second approach is to design a study so
第二種方法是根據指定的統計檢定力
that it will have a specific statistical power.
Now we already saw this graph earlier on in the course.
第一週課程已經看過這張圖
And in this simulation, we have 50% power,
這是設定檢定力50%的模擬結果
which means that 50% of the p-values end up in the leftmost bin.
所以最後有50%的p值集中於最左邊長條
Now, you might think this is too low.
現在大家都知道50%並不高
You want to design a study which has much higher power.
你當然會希望提高研究的檢定力
For example, 95% power.
像是95%
So you can design a a study where you plan for power.
你可以據此設定你的研究
You select the sample size based on the probability of observing a p-value
評估在這條件下，要得到小於0.05的p值
smaller than 0.05.
需要的樣本數
And in these cases we would do a priori power analysis based on an expected
因此你需要設定預期效果量
做事前考驗力分析
effect size.
因此你需要設定預期效果量
做事前考驗力分析
If we take a look at the power for
根據Cohen's d是0.5的獨立t檢定計算檢定力
an independent T test with a coens D of 0.5, we can the sample size
that you need to have a substantial power can become quite large.
能得知要達到檢定力標準的樣本數很大
Very often, if people start to perform power analysis, their first complaint is
許多人經常在做完檢定力分析之後抱怨
that the sample size that's recommended is much larger than they think is necessary.
需要的樣本數比想像中的多太多
Now people seem to have some intuitive feel of the sample
這讓一些人覺得只要說定50%檢定力就夠了
size that they need to achieve 50% power.
As we see, the literature mainly has studies with about 50% power.
但是剛剛就提到
文獻數據的平均檢定力就是50%
So in the beginning, you might be surprised by how many people you need.
所以第一次知道這方法的人
會對評估結果很驚訝
If you want to have about 95% power,
如果想讓研究結果有95%檢定力
you would need a sample size of about 100 people in each condition.
每組人數就要招募100人
Which is quite a lot more than the 15 participants in
比我當年博士論文的每組15人多了好幾倍
each between-subject condition that I designed when I was doing my PhD.
So be prepared for slightly larger sample sizes.
所以請做好增加樣本數的心理準備
Now when you base your power analysis on an effect size from the published
如果要根據文獻的整合效果量做檢定力分析
literature, be very careful.
請務必小心
We know that publication bias inflates effect size estimates in the literature.
已知出版偏誤會誇大效果量的估計值
So you always want to be a little bit more conservative.
因此要採用較保守的評估
A power analysis should be a starting point for
檢定力分析可以做新研究樣本數評估的起點
designing the sample size in a future study.
It should not be the end point.
但絕對不是終點
So always be informed by more than the power analysis itself.
謹記檢定力分析的條件
If you perform a power analysis,
執行一項檢定力分析
always use unbiased effect size estimates in the power analysis.
最好採用不偏誤的效果量估計值
So Hedges' g, epsilon, or omega.
像是Hedges' g, epsilon或omega
If effect sizes are uncertain, there's not a lot to go on in the published
若是效果量不確定，像是文獻數量不足
literature, or there's nothing comparable in the published literature,
缺少可彼此比較的文獻
then sequential analyses are one way to let you look at the data as it comes in,
控制型一錯誤率的序列分析是一種可行的辦法
while controlling your Type 1 error rates.
So if there is huge uncertainty, but
如果幾乎不確定
you still want to achieve a statistically significant result, that's the goal,
但你還是想得到統計顯著的結果
then instead of doing an a priori power analysis, you can use sequential analysis
那不該做事前檢定力分析
而是做序列分析並收集資料直到統計顯著
and collect data until you find a statistically significant effect, or
那不該做事前檢定力分析
而是做序列分析並收集資料直到統計顯著
until you don't want to collect more participants.
或者到不想再收集樣本為止
Now instead of planning for accuracy or power,
除了估計的正確性還有檢定力
it's perfectly fine to plan for feasibility.
研究可行性也是不錯的評估條件
You don't have infinite resources, infinite amount of time or money,
這方法適用在資源，時間和經費有限
or sometimes the population that you want to collect data from is very,
或者要收集的樣本來源很難招募
very difficult to reach.
So in these cases the feasibility of collecting a large sample size
這時收集大樣本資料的可行性
is limited by how easy it is to find participants.
取決於找到合適參與者的便利程度
So, it's perfectly fine to select the sample size based on the time,
這時評估樣本數的最好參考
就是時間、經費、還有招募參與者的便利性
the money, or the participants that you have available.
這時評估樣本數的最好參考
就是時間、經費、還有招募參與者的便利性
This can also be a way to plan a study.
這也是設計研究能考慮的條件
This is just the best that you can do given the resources that you have.
根據手上的研究資源設計研究
And that's perfectly fine.
也是最好的策略
Of course, in these situations, it might be that the statistical power is low, but
當然，這樣可能導致檢定力偏低
in that case you might just want to estimate the effect size,
那麼報告只要提供效果量估計值
instead of performing a statistical test.
不必做統計檢定
You can also use Bayesian statistics.
也可以使用貝氏統計
In Bayesian statistics, you don't have to specify the sample size before you start.
不必去管收集的樣本數
You can collect data and continuing data collection until whenever you want.
收集到你認為結果適當時就好
This quote by Edwards, Lindman, & Savage says,
這段話出自Edwards, Lindman, 與Savage的論文
it is entirely appropriate to collect data until a point has been proven or
資料收集到能確證或否證論點的研究
disproven, or until the data collector runs out of time, money, or patience.
與資料收集到研究者資源耗竭的研究都是一樣好的
If we design a study based on the statistical power, this is a frequentist
以考驗力設計研究和評估樣本數是次數主義思維
approach to designing a study and determining the sample size.
But in Bayesian statistics, you just quantify the evidence that's in the data.
貝氏統計是以手上的資料評估證據力
And if you're not happy with the evidence you have,
今天你不滿意手上資料的證據力
you can always collect more data.
可以繼續收集更多資料
So Bayesian statistics is much more flexible.
貝氏統計本身給予研究者評估的彈性
You can determine the sample size any way you want.
任何決定樣本數的方式都是合理的
On the other hand, there is no easy way to control Type 1 errors.
另一方面，這也造成型一錯誤率不容易控制
It's entirely uncontrolled, but
精確地說是完全沒控制
it's just much more difficult to quantify the Type 1 error rates directly.
並且很難量化型一錯誤率
Nowadays, its becoming increasingly important to justify
今天的研究設計越來越講究評估樣本數
the sample size of a study that you are designing.
In the past, we've seen that people designed underpowered and
過去文獻充斥太多低考驗力的結果
inaccurate studies, and in the future, this really needs to change.
與估計不良的研究
未來這些情勢將被扭轉
The sample size is a very important aspect of the design of a new study.
評估樣本數的設計新研究必做功課
Don't ignore it.
務必謹慎為之
[MUSIC]
影片結束